<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1918 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2826 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2826.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6761 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6761.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6762 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6762.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnsop-onion-tld PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-onion-tld.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902"
  docName="draft-adpkja-dnsop-special-names-problem-00">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Top-Level/Special-Use Domain Names">Problem
      Statement for the Reservation of Top-Level Domains in the
      Special-Use Domain Names Registry</title>

    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>Dyn, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>103-186 Albert Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>N6A 1M1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>jabley@dyn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="P." surname="Koch" fullname="Peter Koch">
      <organization>DENIC</organization>
      <address>
        <email>pk@denic.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="A." surname="Durand" fullname="Alain Durand">
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <email>alain.durand@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="17" month="September" year="2015"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The dominant protocol for name resolution on the Internet
	is the Domain Name System (DNS). However, other protocols
	exist that are fundamentally different from the DNS, but
	which have syntactically-similar namespaces.</t>

      <t>When an end-user triggers resolution of a name on a system
        which supports multiple, different protocols for name resolution,
        it is desirable that the protocol to be used is unambiguous, and
        that requests intended for one protocol are not inadvertently
        addressed using another.</t>

      <t>RFC 6761 introduced a framework by which, under certain
	circumstances, a particular domain name could be acknowledged
	as being special. This framework has been used to make
	top-level domain reservations, that is, particular top-level
	domains that should not be used within the DNS to accommodate
	parallel use of non-DNS name resolution protocols by end-users
	and avoid the possibility of namespace collisions.</t>

      <t>Various challenges have become apparent with this application
	of the guidance provided in RFC 6761.  This document aims
	to document those challenges in the form of a problem
	statement, to facilitate further discussion of potential
	solutions.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>Clear and unambiguous use of terminology is important for
	the clear formulation of any problem statement. The DNS
	protocol suffers from imprecise and overloaded terminology
	(e.g. see <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology"/>)
	without confusing matters further with terms and concepts
	from other naming systems that are similar, but different.</t>

      <t>In the interests of clarity, the following terms used in
        this document are to be interpreted as follows:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t>Aardvark (n): a medium-sized, burrowing, nocturnal mammal
            native to Africa; the only living species of the order
            Tubulidentata. See <eref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aardvark"/>. This is a placeholder.</t>

          <t>Registry (n): the Special-Use Domain Names Registry created
            by <xref target="RFC6761"/> and published at
            <eref target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/special-use-domain-names/special-use-domain-names.xhtml"/></t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>[This section to be completed following review and refinement
       of the rest of the text.]</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The dominant protocol for name resolution on the Internet
	is the Domain Name System (DNS), originally specified in
	<xref target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/>.
	However, other name resolution protocols exist that are
	fundamentally different from the DNS, but which make use of
	syntactically-similar namespaces.</t>

      <t>When an end-user triggers resolution of a name on a system
	which supports multiple, different name resolution protocols,
	it is desirable that the protocol to be used is unambiguous
	and that requests intended for one protocol are not
	inadvertently addressed using another.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC6761"/> introduced a framework by which,
	under certain circumstances, a particular domain name could
	be acknowledged as being special. This framework has been
	used to make a reservation (a part of the DNS namespace
	that should not be used by the DNS protocol) to accommodate
	non-DNS name resolution protocols and to avoid the possibility
	of namespace collisions.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC6761"/> describes seven questions which
	should be considered when deciding whether a domain name
	is special.  Domain names that are acknowledged to be special
	are inserted into the Registry, the initial contents of
	which included 25 entries; four were top-level domains
	(TEST, LOCALHOST, INVALID and EXAMPLE).  Following the
	publication of <xref target="RFC6761"/>, the top-level
	domain names "LOCAL" <xref target="RFC6762"/> and "ONION"
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-onion-tld"/> were added.</t>

      <t>While some of the entries in the Registry document
	the use of a DNS-like namespace by non-DNS name resolution
	protocols (LOCALHOST, LOCAL, ONION), other entries are
	included for different reasons (e.g. EXAMPLE.ORG, EXAMPLE.COM
	and EXAMPLE.NET are reserved for use in documentation;
	so-called reverse zones corresponding to <xref target="RFC1918"/>
	addresses are special in the sense that they are usually
	non-unique).</t>

      <t>This document specifically explores the problems in the
	use of <xref target="RFC6761"/> to justify the reservation
	of top-level domains in the DNS. Use of <xref target="RFC6761"/>
	with reference to other domain names is not discussed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Clear and Specific Guidelines" anchor="justification">
      <t><xref target="RFC6761"/> (section 5) describes seven
	questions to be answered in order to provide clear guidance
	about how and why a particular domain name is special. These
	seven questions can be broadly categorised as follows:

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>impact on end-users;</t>

          <t>impact on applications;</t>

          <t>impact on name resolution APIs and libraries;</t>

          <t>impact on recursive resolvers;</t>

          <t>impact on authoritative DNS servers;</t>

          <t>impact on DNS server operators;</t>

          <t>impact on DNS registries and registrars.</t>
        </list>

        Answers to these seven questions provide guidance to
        various audiences on how to handle a special-use domain name
        once it has been registered. However, they are inadequate
        for determining whether a particular domain name qualifies
        as being special and should be included in the Registry.</t>

      <t>Experience with the review and ultimate approval of <xref
	target="RFC6762"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-onion-tld"/>
	has revealed a need for objective criteria and a clear
	process that encourages and facilitates useful registrations
	of top-level domains in the Registry without fear of abuse,
	and with consistent and adequate consideration of all future
        requests.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Evaluation Process">
      <t><xref target="RFC6762"/> specifies the way in which "an
        IETF 'Standards Action' or 'IESG Approval' document" should
        present answers to the questions described in
        <xref target="justification"/>, but does not describe the
        process by which the answers should be evaluated.</t>

      <t>For example, it is not clear whether the evaluation of a
	document which requests additions to the Registry should
	be performed by the IESG, by the IAB, by the DNSOP working
	group, by an ad-hoc working group, by expert review or any
	combination of those approaches.</t>

      <t>At the time of writing, the DNSOP working group charter
        does not clearly indicate that DNSOP is the proper venue
        for the evaluation to be carried out, although it also does
        not prohibit this work taking place there.</t>

      <t>As an illustration of the inconsistency that has been
	observed already, <xref target="RFC6762"/> was published
	as an AD-sponsored individual submission in the INT area,
	and the IESG evaluation record does not reveal any discussion
	of the reservation of the LOCAL top-level domain in the
	DNS; <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-onion-tld"/>, however,
	was published as a working group document through DNSOP,
	and an extensive discussion by the IESG on the merits of
	the request took place.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Coordination between the IETF and ICANN">
      <t>The policy surrounding the implementation and management
	of top-level domains in the DNS has been developed using a
	multi-stakeholder process convened by ICANN. At the time
	of writing, the process by which most new top-level domains
	are reviewed includes the ability for applications to be
	rejected on technical grounds; for example, an application
	for "LOCALHOST" would not be approved.</t>

      <t>Whilst discussing the particular attributes that make a
	domain name special, <xref target="RFC6761"/> notes that
	"the act of defining such a special name creates a higher-level
	protocol rule, above ICANN's management of allocatable names
	on the public Internet." This declaration may well be
	uncontentious, perhaps accommodated by the technical review
	alluded to above. However, a clear understanding of the
	operational coordination required to avoid conflicts seems
	prudent, in the interests of maintaining the stability of
	the naming system as a whole and protecting end-users from
	confusion or harm.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Clear Expectations">
      <t>Each of the seven questions posed by <xref target="RFC6761"/>
	has the potential to expose special handling of particular
	queries in the DNS by particular audiences. However, it is
	not clear what any of those audiences might reasonably
        expect as a result of a succesful request to add a top-level
        domain to the Registry.</t>

      <t>For example, reservation of a top-level domain by the IETF
	does not guarantee that queries for names within a reserved
	domain will not be sent over the Internet. The requirements
	of the operators of recursive resolvers in the DNS cannot
	be relied upon to be implemented; the impact on the operators
	of DNS authoritative servers hence cannot be reliably assumed
	to be zero. In the case of <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-onion-tld"/>, leakage of ONION queries
	on the Internet might lead to disclosure of private information
	that, in some cases, might pose a risk to the personal
	safety of end-users.</t>

      <t>The Registry as published at the time of writing does not
        include direct guidance for any of the seven audiences,
        relying instead upon a reference to a published RFC that
        might well be opaque to many readers (<xref target="RFC6762"/>
        is a seventy-page protocol specification, for example, which
        is arguably not the most expressive way to set expectations of
        non-technical end-users).</t>

      <t>Useful reservations of top-level domains should be accompanied
	by the existence of realistic expectations of each of the
	seven audiences, and the evaluation of particular requests
	should consider the practical liklihood of those expectations
	being met and the implications if they are not.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Identifiers in Names">
      <t>At the time of writing, three top-level domain names reserved
        by inclusion in the Registry are used by name resolution
        protocols other than the DNS:

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="LOCALHOST">is used to refer to the host on which
            the name resolution takes place, without reference to the
            DNS;</t>

	  <t hangText="LOCAL">is used by the Multicast DNS protocol
            specified in <xref target="RFC6762"/> which is similar in
            some respects to the DNS, but which uses a different
            well-known port number and is limited to a particular
            multicast scope;</t>

          <t hangText="ONION">is used to construct names that
            designate anonymous hidden services reachable via the Tor
            network using onion routing.</t>
	</list>

	The three name resolution protocols described above are
	different from the DNS, and the namespaces used in each
	naming scheme are also different (if similar, in some cases).
        The top-level label is hence effectively being used as a
        name resolution protocol identifier.</t>

      <t>The lack of a more elegant way to specify a name resolution
	protocol in (for example) a URI amounts to an architectural
	problem. However, it is not clear that this is still a
	problem that can be solved; it could be observed that in
	the absence of a more elegant alternative, a pragmatic
	choice to embed priotocol selectors as namespace tokens has
	effectively already been made. Although the reservation of
	names in the DNS namespace can be made at any level, the
	three examples above demonstrate use-cases for reservation
	at the top-level, and hence that case must be considered.</t>

      <t>In <xref target="RFC2826"/> the IAB noted that

        <list style="empty">
          <t>To remain a global network, the Internet requires the
            existence of a globally unique public name space.
            The DNS name space is a hierarchical name space derived
            from a single, globally unique root."</t>
        </list>

        Maintaining a globally-unique public namespace that supports
        different name resolution protocols is hence an architectural
        requirement, and some facility for reservation of top-level
        domains in the DNS is necessary.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Separation of Protocol and Policy">
      <t><xref target="RFC6761"/> does not address the choice of
        domain name to be added to the Registry when considering a
        particular case of special-use.</t>

      <t>In the case of LOCALHOST, LOCAL and ONION, use of particular
        domain names was already in use by a substantial population of
        end-users, and the practical cost of a transition perhaps
        justifies their continued use. However, when formulating a
        general process for future such reservations, prior use of
        particular names cannot be assumed.</t>

      <t>In the case where the technical requirement is for reservation
	of a unique domain name, and not any domain name in particular,
	the IETF should consider whether the choice of name is
	really a technical matter, or a policy decision that is
	best addressed in other venues.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document aims to provide a problem statement that
	will inform future work. Whilst security and privacy are
	fundamental considerations, this document expects that that
	future work will include such analysis, and hence no attempt
	is made to do so here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Your name here, etc.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1034;
      &rfc1035;
      &rfc6761;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc1918;
      &rfc2826;
      &rfc6762;

      &I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-terminology;
      &I-D.ietf-dnsop-onion-tld;
    </references>

    <section title="Editorial Notes">
      <t>This section (and sub-sections) to be removed prior to
        publication.</t>

      <section title="Venue">
        <t>An appropriate forum for discussion of this draft is
          the dnsop working group.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Pithy Quotes from History">
        <t>
          <list style="empty">
	    <t>The question has arisen as to how the toplevel naming
	      authority decides who gets a toplevel name and who
	      must get by with a non-toplevel name.  The suggestion
	      was made by MOCKAPETRIS@USC-ISIF that perhaps the
	      existing toplevel nameholders might vote on whether
	      the applicant for a new toplevel name should be
	      granted, with a majority needed for approval. It seems
	      to me this might produce a clique whereby whoever
	      initially gains power will hold it and prevent its
	      "enemies" from getting in too. This will make the
	      toplevel rather less than universal.</t>
          </list>

          (E-mail from Robert Elton Maas to the namedroppers mailing
          list on 9 November 1983)</t>

        <t>
          <list style="empty">
	    <t>My basic point is that as a world-wide network evolves
	      it is ridiculous to force people to name resources
	      in terms of one static hierarchy which very closely
	      resembles the current internetwork topology (as the
	      current scheme does).  What we are eventually going
	      to require is a distributed expert for making sense
	      out of a name someone hands it.  There will be no
	      simple algorithm to be written on one page of an RFC
	      that will suffice to resolve a name.  Rather, a number
	      of heuristics will let a resolver make sense out of
	      a given name by querying other experts which it
	      suspects may be more knowledgeable about the name
	      than it is, or by forwarding a piece of mail to an
	      expert which is at least one level closer to the
	      destination in some hierarchy.</t>
          </list>

          (E-mail from Peter Karp to the namedroppers mailing list
          on 8 February 1984)</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Change History">
        <section title="draft-adpkja-special-names-problem-00">
          <t>Initial draft circulated for comment.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

